<!doctype html>
<html>
	<head>
		<meta charset="utf-8">
		<meta http-equiv="X-UA-Compatible" content="chrome=1">
		<meta name="description" content="Yashas Kumar's Personal Website">
		<title></title>

		<link rel="stylesheet" href="/static/css/styles.css">
		<link rel="stylesheet" href="/static/css/pygment_trac.css">
		<script src="/static/js/scale.fix.js"></script>
		<meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1, user-scalable=no">
		
		<script>
		  (function(i,s,o,g,r,a,m){i['GoogleAnalyticsObject']=r;i[r]=i[r]||function(){
		  (i[r].q=i[r].q||[]).push(arguments)},i[r].l=1*new Date();a=s.createElement(o),
		  m=s.getElementsByTagName(o)[0];a.async=1;a.src=g;m.parentNode.insertBefore(a,m)
		  })(window,document,'script','//www.google-analytics.com/analytics.js','ga');
			
		  ga('create', 'UA-42181956-1', 'yrkumar.github.io');
		  ga('send', 'pageview');
		</script>

	</head>
	
	<body>
		<div class="wrapper" id="wrapper">
			<header>
				<h1><a href="/">Yashas Kumar</a></h1>
				<br>
				<h4><span style="font-weight:normal">I'm a Software Engineer at <a href="https://www.facebook.com/" target="_new">Facebook</a>. Previously, I studied Computer Science at <a href="https://www.cmu.edu/" target="_new">Carnegie Mellon University</a>. Connect with me on <a href="https://linkedin.com/in/yrkumar" target="_new">LinkedIn</a>.</span></h4>
			</header>
      		
			<section id="main">
        			<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

	<title>yrkumar</title>
	<link href="http://yrkumar.githug.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="http://yrkumar.github.io/"/>
	<updated>2022-02-11T10:35:40-07:00</updated>
		<id>http://yrkumar.github.io</id>
	<author>
		<name>Yashas Kumar</name>
	</author>
	
	
	<entry>
		<title>A Safe Framework for Managing Personal Finances</title>
		<link href="http://yrkumar.github.io/posts/A-Safe-Framework-for-Managing-Personal-Finances"/>
		<updated>2022-01-06T01:00:00-07:00</updated>
		<id>http://yrkumar.github.io/posts/A-Safe-Framework-for-Managing-Personal-Finances</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are three core principles that form the basis of a reasonably safe personal money management strategy for the wide majority of people under salaried employment in the United States. We’ll go through them here one-by-one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Invest rather than save.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a fundamental level, money is valuable because it allows for purchasing goods and services. However, in an inflationary world, the purchasing power of a static amount of money decreases over time. In 2021, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bls.gov/opub/ted/2021/consumer-prices-up-6-8-percent-for-year-ended-november-2021.htm&quot;&gt;the CPI (Consumer Price Index)&lt;/a&gt;, which tracks the change in prices paid by consumers for goods and services, went up by 6.8%. Therefore, if your personal wealth grew by less than 6.8% in 2021 then you have actually become poorer because you have less buying power relative to beginning of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Use retirement accounts.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retirement accounts (e.g. 401k, IRA) are tax advantaged relative to other investment vehicles. In a normal brokerage account, your money is taxed twice - first, when you earn the income (via income tax) and then again when you realize profit by selling an asset (via capital gains tax). In comparison, retirement accounts are only taxed once, either when the money goes into the account (post-tax or Roth) or when the money comes out of the account (pre-tax or traditional).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s do some math to compare the same investment in different accounts. For simplicity, we will assume a flat income and capital gains tax rate of 30% and a return of 100% on an initial investment of $100,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/investments.png&quot; alt=&quot;Investment vs Retirement Accounts&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tax advantaged accounts skip a tax step, making them strictly better than the brokerage accounts. The only caveat here is that some retirement accounts charge a penalty for withdrawing money from them before a certain age, so if you’re looking for near term liquidity, then skip this money management principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Take advantage of tax and asset class diversification.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diversification is a good way to hedge against the risk of concentrating your investment in specific strategies or assets. There are many avenues to diversify investments, but two that are significant are tax diversification and asset class diversification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tax diversification means allocating assets in accounts with differing taxation strategies. The goal is to protect investments against tax uncertainty in the future (e.g. from regulation). On a practical basis, this means splitting your investments between pre-tax and post-tax retirement accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asset class diversification is pretty straightforward - it means making sure that your portfolio is not overbalanced on any single asset or asset class. The idea here is to protect investments against a single tanking asset or sector. On a practical basis, this means investing in broad based index funds.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Making Life Easier for CMU Students</title>
		<link href="http://yrkumar.github.io/posts/Making-Life-Easier-for-CMU-Students"/>
		<updated>2013-07-09T01:00:00-06:00</updated>
		<id>http://yrkumar.github.io/posts/Making-Life-Easier-for-CMU-Students</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over this past winter break, I was registering for classes using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cmu.edu/hub/fce/&quot;&gt;Carnegie Mellon’s Faculty Course Evaluations&lt;/a&gt; (FCE) to help me decide which courses to take. A tool provided by CMU, FCE gathers ratings data by recording student responses to surveys distributed online after each semester ends. These ratings provide a goldmine of information on almost every course offered at CMU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I browsed the site, I realized that it was taking me a while just to find different courses and see how their evaluations matched up (I can’t place the blame fully on CMU; FCE seems to be operated by an external company). Although it’s a great resource for finding data about courses, FCE wasn’t living up to its potential as a powerful course comparison tool… Why? Mostly because of its interface:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/fceInterface.png&quot; alt=&quot;FCE Interface&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An almost endless drop down menu to narrow options? Semesters worth of ratings data squished into one REALLY big table of values on a single page? I found myself resorting to ctrl-f to find each course I was interested in and then writing down the evaluations as I went so I could do a comprehensive comparison. After almost an hour of frustration, I finally gave up and decided to try and fix it so that I wouldn’t have to repeat the process for future semesters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using Python and a handy framework called &lt;a href=&quot;http://scrapy.org/&quot;&gt;Scrapy&lt;/a&gt;, I created a simple data crawler to scrape the course evaluations off of FCE and serialize them for easy storage. After running the crawler and gathering the ratings data in a file, I built a front-end search interface with &lt;a href=&quot;http://flask.pocoo.org/&quot;&gt;Flask&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.github.io/bootstrap/&quot;&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; to parse search queries that could be made by users, returning the course ratings that matched those queries in a neat and organized table:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/whichCourse.png&quot; alt=&quot;WhichCourse Interface&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I called the app WhichCourse because I created it to help me choose which courses to take. WhichCourse offers two major advantages over FCE for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allows searching for multiple course at once for easy side-by-side comparison&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aggregates course evaluations (displayed by semester in FCE) to show a comprehensive rating for each course and professor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Bonus): Provides a slick, bootstrapped interface to view data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through building WhichCourse, I realized how useless data without organization is. Even though the amount of data in FCE is nowhere near the amount processed by modern day Big Data companies, it still was an immense pain to access when it was unindexed. See &lt;a href=&quot;http://whichcourse.herokuapp.com/&quot;&gt;WhichCourse&lt;/a&gt; live in action or &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/yrkumar/which-course&quot;&gt;browse the source code on Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a sidenote, I had a great time using Flask and would really recommend it for simple web apps or for prototyping larger Django projects. For example, error handling for WhichCourse (when the user entered a malformed search query) was as simple as utilizing Flask’s built-in &lt;a href=&quot;http://jinja.pocoo.org/&quot;&gt;Jinja2&lt;/a&gt; templating system to display different messages on screen depending on the variety of the error. Here’s an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/yrkumar/199d22d3b3088c6a7f4c.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, the conditionals easily catch malformed search queries and render different HTML templates based on the status of these queries. Aside from an awesome templating system, Flask aslo boasts an awesome built-in debugger and great &lt;a href=&quot;http://flask.pocoo.org/docs/&quot;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
	</entry>
	
 
</feed>

      			</section>
      
			<footer>
        		<p><small>Hosted on <a href="http://pages.github.com" target-"_new">GitHub Pages</a> &mdash; Theme by <a href="https://github.com/orderedlist" target="_new">orderedlist</a></small></p>
			</footer>

    		</div>
	</body>
</html>

